<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl"
	href="http://docbook.sourceforge.net/release/xsl-ns/current/html/docbook.xsl"?>
<article version="5.0"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <info>
    <title>Alien Arena for Linux on Desura</title>
    <author>
      <orgname>COR Entertainment, LLC.</orgname>
    </author>
    <copyright>
      <year>2012</year>
      <holder>COR Entertainment, LLC.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <releaseinfo>$Id$</releaseinfo>
  </info>
  
  <section xml:id="About">
    <title>About this Document</title>
    <para>
      This document is a reference for installing and maintaining Alien
      Arena on the Desura digital distribution service, http://www.desura.com.
    </para>
    <para>
      Currently (January 2013), this covers the Linux versions.
    </para>
    <para>
      This document is DocBook 5. The formatting program is
      <application>xsltproc</application>. The stylesheet is
      <filename>docbook/xsl-ns-stylesheets/html/docbook.xsl</filename>,
      which is specified within the heading.  So, providing docbook support
      is installed,  a script to generate the <filename>.html</filename>
      file is something like this:
      <programlisting>#!/bin/sh
xsltproc -o devref-desura-en.html docsrc/devref-desura-en.xml</programlisting>
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="Support">
    <title>Support</title>
    <para>
      Finding and deciphering the documentation for installing Desura,
      installing games from Desura, and distributing games on Desura is a bit
      of a chore. The adminstrators are helpful and respond quickly, though.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Linux-related forum is at: 
      <link xlink:href="http://www.desura.com/groups/desura/linux">
        http://www.desura.com/groups/desura/linux
      </link>
    </para>
    <para>
      There is a Wiki at:
      <link xlink:href="https://trac.moddb.com/app/wiki/">
        https://trac.moddb.com/app/wiki
      </link>
      (It may not be well-maintained, and could be out-of-date.)
    </para>
    <para>
      This document assumes the initial setup for publication has been
      done. Only updating an existing project is covered here.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="Overview">
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>
      Desura requires a binary executable that runs in the user's home
      directory.  The builds for 7.60.1 AND 7.65 were done using Ubuntu
      12.04 LTS.  Separate OS installations were used for x86 and x86_64.
    </para>
    <note>
      <title>Potential future headaches</title>
      <para>
        The new Steam Linux implementation is similar. Currently, Steam
        officially supports only Ubuntu. Desura's solution to problem
        of supporting different Linux OS's, is to load various versions
        of system libraries into the user's home directory. Steam may do
        something similar in the future.  This technique is probably not a
        good thing. It does not conform to common Linux standards, but, more
        importantly, it will probably be a gigantic headache for developers.
      </para>
    </note>
    
    <para>
      These are the major steps for installation on Desura:
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Create the system build environments</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Create the build</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Create the installation directory</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Create documents customized for Desura</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify the dependencies and install settings</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Create and upload the MCF</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Commit, get approval and test</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Upload the release tarball</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="SystemEnvironments">
    <title>Create the System Environments</title>
    <para>
      Updating Desura requires a Desura/IndieDB/ModDB account, of course,
      and, also developer access rights. (Access rights management can be
      accessed through the Alien Arena Publish page; under the Profile list,
      click on Access Rights.)
    </para>
    <para>
      There are 2 OS system environments; 32-bit Linux x86 and 64-bit
      Linux x86-64.  One could use either one and cross-compile to the
      other. However, for testing purposes and for uploading to Desura it
      may be best to have separate installations.  Ideally, this does not
      need to be done for every release. Once the system environments are
      in operation, they may be used for later releases.
    </para>
    <para>
      For 7.60, I chose to use Ubuntu 12.04 LTS and create a multi-boot
      environment on Gentoo x86 using "legacy" GRUB. The Ubuntu partitions are
      about 30G each on a second drive using Extended Partitions.  The setup
      one uses, of course, is mostly a matter of taste. The following is an
      example and some notes.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Ubuntu installation is not particularly happy with this arrangement,
      and it requires some magic.  When installing from a DVD, after
      selecting "Try Ubuntu", in a terminal do: <userinput>ubiquity
      --no-bootloader</userinput> This prevents the installer,
      <filename>ubiquity</filename>, from trying to create a boot sector
      and install GRUB 2. The additions to <filename>grub.conf</filename>
      look like this:
    </para>
    <para>
      <literallayout><emphasis>
title=Ubuntu Linux x86 (3.2.0-xx-generic-pae)
root (hd1,4)
kernel /vmlinuz  root=/dev/sdb5
initrd /initrd.img

title=Ubuntu Linux x86_64 (3.2.0.xx-generic)
root (hd1,5)
kernel /vmlinuz root=/dev/sdb6
initrd /initrd.img
        </emphasis></literallayout>
    </para>
    <para>
      And at the top level of the partitions, these soft links supply
      references to the kernel boot files.
    </para>
    <para>
      <literallayout><emphasis>
for x86:
vmlinuz -> boot/vmlinuz-3.2.0-32-generic-pae
initrd.img -> /boot/initrd.img-3.2.0-32-generic-pae

for x86-64:
vmlinuz -> boot/vmlinuz-3.2.0-32-generic
initrd.img -> /boot/initrd.img-3.2.0-32-generic
        </emphasis>
      </literallayout>
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="Build">
    <title>Create the Build</title>
    <para>
      The directory for the build is separate from the Desura installation
      directory. Normally, it would be created by unpacking a release tarball
      according to usual instructions.
    </para>
    <para>
      For Linux, Desura installs into the users home directory, so the
      <emphasis>alternate install</emphasis> configuration is used. The
      compiler options should follow distro packaging practice for generating
      an executable to run on different architectures. Distro's also use
      stack protection, which is a good idea in this case.
    </para>
    <para>
      <command>export CFLAGS='-O2 -mtune=generic -fstack-protector-all
        --param=ssp-buffer-size=4 -D_FORTIFY_SOURCE=2'
      </command>
    </para>
    <para>
      <command>export CXXFLAGS='-O2 -mtune=generic
        -fstack-protector-all --param=ssp-buffer-size=4
        -D_FORTIFY_SOURCE=2'
      </command>
    </para>
    <para>
      <command>./configure --enable-alternate-install</command>
    </para>
    <para>
      To keep things simpler, the integrated libode should be used.
      Other configure options that are probably preferred are:
    </para>
    <para>
      <command>--enable-maintainer-mode --disable-silent-rules</command>
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="InstallationDirectory">
    <title>Create the Installation Directory</title>
    <para>
      For Desura, the installation directory is created separately.  This may
      not be strictly necessary, but if the build directory were used a
      lot of unnecessary files would be included.  (Just FYI, according
      to documentation, Desura will filter out <filename>.svn</filename>
      subdirectories.)
    </para>
    <para>
      The installation directory is normally, and officially, named
      <filename>alien-arena-2008</filename>.  Other names may be used,
      but Desura will install in the official directory on the user's
      system.
    </para>
    <para>
      The contents of the installation directory are:
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <filename>alienarena</filename>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            The Linux binary.
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <filename>README</filename>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            The Desura custom top-level readme file (see below)
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <filename>arena/motd.txt</filename>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            The stock message-of-the-day file
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <filename class="directory">botinfo/</filename>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            All the bot and nav files in the release
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <filename class="directory">data1/</filename>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            All the game resource files in the release
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <filename class="directory">docs/</filename>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            Documentation customized for Desura (see below)
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      The Linux dedicated server is not included on purpose.
      It is assumed that a user would download the full tarball,
      if there was an interest in running that.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="CustomDocuments">
    <title>Customize Documents for Desura</title>
    
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <filename>README</filename>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          A special README for Desura pointing to the other documents in
          the doc subdirectory.  Has information about the compiler and
          configuration used to generate the binary for Desura.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <filename>GAME_README.TXT</filename>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          This is the general <filename>readme.txt</filename> reformatted for
          Linux.  If that file is modified, then this one should be updated.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <filename>TECH_README.TXT</filename>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          This is the top-level Unix/Linux README.
          The changed name is the only difference.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <filename>LICENSE.TXT</filename>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          This is the COR Entertainment, LLC. copyright and license.  The same
          content as <filename>license.txt</filename> reformatted for Linux.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <filename>GPL.TXT</filename>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          The GNU GENERAL PUBLIC LICENSE, Version 2.
        </listitem>
        
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <filename>LGPL.TXT</filename>
        </term>
        <term>
          <filename>ODE_LICENSE.TXT</filename>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          The GNU LESSER GENERAL PUBLIC LICENSE Version 2.1 and
          the Open Dynamics Engine (ODE) License.  Included because
          the Desura binary uses the integrated ODE version of the
          <filename>alienarena</filename> build.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="VerifySettings">
    <title>Verify the Dependencies and Install Settings</title>
    <para>
      If the program adds a shared library to its link, the install settings
      may need updating. Otherwise, install settings do not usually need to
      be modified. It is a good idea to verify the settings in any case.
    </para>
    <para>
      Here is a menu sequence for getting to the Alien Arena Publish
      page:
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>Play</listitem>
      <listitem>On the Toolbar line (after Games and Favorities), Development
      </listitem>
      <listitem>Right Click on AlienArena</listitem>
      <listitem>Tools</listitem> 
      <listitem>Desura Page (tab name is "Publish")</listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
      Once on the Publish page, on the Releases list, click on Upload.
      Then, click on the Full Linux, and Full Linux 64 branches and verify
      that the Dependencies are correct.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Install Settings, also on the Releases list, control the program
      file paths and should not be changed.
    </para>
    
  </section>
   
  
  <section xml:id="UploadMCF">
    <title>Create and Upload the MCF</title>
    <para>
      The Managed Content File (MCF) is a Desura proprietary format used
      to upload to the Desura Server. It is generated by Desura-supplied
      procedures which calculate the difference between the current released
      installation and the new version.
    </para>
    <para>
      Initially, it can be confusing because the user-interface can be
      mysterious.  The clickable links for the next step in the multi-step
      process sometimes appear only after the current step is completed,
      so it takes some "leaps of faith."  When there are no errors, the
      process is easy. But when upload errors occur clearing the broken
      upload and restarting does not always work.
    </para>
    <para>
      Late in the process, a request for the changelog appears. It requires
      changelog entries in a specific format. If possible, prepare this
      beforehand.  Use the changelog for the Windows version, if it is
      available.
    </para>
    <para>
      Once the Installation Directory is ready, the MCF can be created and
      uploaded.  Make sure the directory is clean with no extraneous files. If
      the binary was built with debug symbols, they should be stripped.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Create MCF command can be accessed through Play Menu. Access like
      the sequence above, click on Create MCF rather than Desura Page.
      Enter the path to the installation directory and wait. On success,
      click on Upload MCF and upload the newly created MCF.
    </para>
    <para>
      These commands may also be accessed through the Alien Arena Publish
      page. Select Upload in the Release list. Then scroll to the Upload
      section at the bottom of the page.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the upload fails, clearing the upload and starting over does not
      always work. Consult the support resources for work-arounds.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="CommitMCF">
    <title>Commit the MCF, Get Approval, Test</title>
    <para>
      Once the MCF is successfully uploaded, there will be a Submit for
      Approval command on the Publish page.  Desura administrators usually
      approve in a few days.
    </para>
    <para>      
      At that point, the <emphasis>test</emphasis> command is activated.
      On a system with an existing installation, it will be updated with
      changes.  In case this is not obvious: this is not the same as the
      installation directory used to generate the MCF.  It will be found in the
      <filename>desura/common</filename> directory in the user home directory.
      It is probably a good idea to test a clean install, also.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="UploadTarball">
    <title>Upload the Release Tarball</title>
    <para>
      Desura calls this the <emphasis>standalone</emphasis>. The standalone
      upload page can be accessed through the Upload section or by clicking
      on the existing standalone package listing. The tarball download is
      listed as the 32-bit version; uploading a 64-bit labeled version
      would be redundant.
    </para>
    
  </section>
  
</article>

